<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on George Hotten</title><link>/blog/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on George Hotten</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/blog/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Barriers to Communication &amp; How to Overcome them</title><link>/blog/posts/barriers-to-communication/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/posts/barriers-to-communication/</guid><description>Whilst presenting or trying to communicate a message, there are often many barriers and issues that must be considered before presenting to ensure that your communication is effective. This post will examine them and look at the ways these barriers can be overcome.
Language Barrier Not everyone in the world speaks the same language and will be able to understand yours, meaning that people who speak a different language to you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to understand your message.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Whilst presenting or trying to communicate a message, there are often many barriers and issues that must be considered before presenting to ensure that your communication is effective. This post will examine them and look at the ways these barriers can be overcome.</p>
<h2 id="language-barrier">Language Barrier</h2>
<p>Not everyone in the world speaks the same language and will be able to understand yours, meaning that people who speak a different language to you won&rsquo;t be able to understand your message. One way to get around this is to hire translators to translate your message. Alternately, translation software can be used to do this automatically. Cultural differences can also be an issue, therefore it is important to understand your audience and their lifestyle so that you don&rsquo;t accidentally cause offence.</p>
<h2 id="auditory-impairment">Auditory Impairment</h2>
<p>Many people struggle with their hearing which could make it hard for them to understand what you are saying, or they may not even be able to hear you at all. This means they won&rsquo;t be able to understand the message you are trying to deliver. A few ways to overcome this barrier would be to hire an interpreter who can provide sign language for the audience, or you could use dictation software which will understand what you are saying and display subtitles on a screen for the hearing impaired to use. Alternately, a hearing-aid microphone could be used to assist their hearing.</p>
<h2 id="background-noise">Background Noise</h2>
<p>If there is lots of noise in the background whilst you are presenting, it will make it hard for your audience to listen and for them to stay engaged with your presentation. This can be overcome by making sure you deliver your presentation in a quiet area. Devices such as air conditioning or fans may also contribute to problematic background noise - if they can be turned off, they should be.</p>
<h2 id="distractions">Distractions</h2>
<p>If there is noise from people talking in the audience, or if phones are constantly going off, it will make it hard for the audience to stay focused on your presentation. Make sure everyone attending silences their devices and ask people to respect you but not speaking during the presentation. Also ensure people who may need to leave early are seated near to the exit so they do not cause a disruption. Similarly, ensure any late arrivals are seated where they won&rsquo;t cause a disruption to those already in place.</p>
<h2 id="lack-of-engagement">Lack of Engagement</h2>
<p>If your presentation / delivery isn&rsquo;t done with enthusiasm and excitement and doesn&rsquo;t include any audience interaction, it will cause your audience to become disinterested in your delivery meaning they will stop listening. Ensure that your delivery is made with positive body language and with a lively and excited attitude. Also make sure your presentation gives a chance for the audience to participate and give them a chance to voice their opinions.</p>
<h2 id="technology-failures">Technology Failures</h2>
<p>There is always a chance that there could be a power outage, the computer you are using to present could crash or your internet could go out. Whilst mitigating all of these can be hard, you should always have backup plans just in case they occur. Some mitigations could be: use a laptop so if power is lost, the laptop won&rsquo;t shutdown as it will continue to run on the battery; have a printed version of the presentation prepared in case the projector fails, use a UPS to keep power if there is an outage; have a spare computer available in case yours fails.</p>
<h2 id="not-speaking-clearly">Not Speaking Clearly</h2>
<p>If you are mumbling, slurring or stuttering your words it may make it harder for your audience to understand what you are saying. Whilst if this is caused by a medical problem, it cannot be helped, but consider using subtitles for your audience to assist them. This is also true if you have a strong regional accent. Subtitles can be really useful. Always ensure that you speak confidently and as clearly as you can whilst presenting.</p>
<h2 id="lack-of-structure">Lack of Structure</h2>
<p>If there is not a clear structure to your presentation, it will make it hard for your audience to understand and follow. Ensure that everything is checked before the presentation to ensure that your slides are in the correct order, and everything flows together.</p>
<h2 id="lack-of-organisation--lack-of-time">Lack of Organisation / Lack of Time</h2>
<p>Make sure that you allow enough time to complete your presentation without rushing through it. Make sure you pick a date and time where you know you and your audience have availability so everyone has time to focus on the delivery. You must also ensure you plan everything you will present in advance and have everything needed for the presentation prepared before the presentation is meant to begin.</p>
<h2 id="lack-of-knowledge-of-the-topic">Lack of Knowledge of the Topic</h2>
<p>If you are delivering a presentation about IT to a non-IT audience, make sure you only use terminology that the audience will be able to understand. For example, using specialist IT terms to the audience would be no use as they would not know the technical IT jargon. If you are making any words simpler, make sure it’s not done in a patronising way as it may disengage your audience and make them feel like they are not respected.</p>
<p>Taking all of these barriers into account, I hope you can use the ideas to overcome them and to improve your delivery and refine your skills as a presenter.</p>
]]></content></item></channel></rss>