<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on George Hotten</title><link>/blog/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on George Hotten</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/blog/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Barriers to Communication</title><link>/blog/posts/barriers-to-communication/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/posts/barriers-to-communication/</guid><description>Whilst presenting or tyring to communicate a message, there are often many barriers and issues that must be considered before presenting to ensure that your communication is effective. This will also go over some ways these barriers can be broken.
Language Barrier Not everyone in the world speaks the same language and will be able to understand yours, meaning that people who speak a different language to you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to understand your message.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Whilst presenting or tyring to communicate a message, there are often many barriers and issues that must be considered before presenting to ensure that your communication is effective. This will also go over some ways these barriers can be broken.</p>
<h1 id="language-barrier">Language Barrier</h1>
<p>Not everyone in the world speaks the same language and will be able to understand yours, meaning that people who speak a different language to you won&rsquo;t be able to understand your message. One way to get around this would to be to hire translators to translate what you are saying to the people who cannot understand. Alternately, translation software could be used to do this automatically.</p>
<h1 id="auditory-impairment">Auditory Impairment</h1>
<p>Many people struggle with their hearing which could make it hard for them to understand what you are saying, or they may not even be able to hear you at all. This means they won&rsquo;t be able to understand the message you are trying to deliver. A few ways to overcome this barrier would be to hire an interpreter who can do sign language for the audience, or you could use dictatory software which will understand what you are saying and display subtitles on a screen for the hearing impaired to use. Alternately, a hearing-aid microphone could be used to assist their hearing.</p>
]]></content></item></channel></rss>